Translator: Joseph Geni Reviewer: Camille Martínez
翻訳: Shoko Takaki 校正: Takamitsu Hirono
I am a chef
私は料理人で
and a food policy guy,
栄養政策担当者ですが
but I come from a whole family of teachers.
家族全員が 教員の家庭で育ちました
My sister is a special ed teacher in Chicago.
姉はシカゴで 特別支援学校の教員をしています
My father just retired after 25 years teaching fifth grade.
父は25年間５年生を受け持った後 退職をしたばかりです
My aunt and uncle were professors.
叔母と叔父は教授でした
My cousins all teach.
従妹は皆教員です
Everybody in my family, basically, teaches except for me.
基本的に私以外 家族の全員が教員なのです
They taught me that the only way to get the right answers
家族には こう教わりました
So what are the right questions
では 子ども達の学習成果を 改善するための
There's obviously many important questions,
大切な質問が数多くあることは もちろんですが
but I think the following is a good place to start:
こんな問いから始めては いかがでしょうか
What do we think the connection is
子どもの心と体の成長には どんな関係があるのでしょうか？
What can we expect our kids to learn
もし子ども達の食事が 砂糖まみれで栄養価に乏しければ
if their diets are full of sugar and empty of nutrients?
彼らに何を 学ばせられるでしょうか？
What can they possibly learn
子どもの体が まさに飢餓状態にあるとしたら
And with all the resources that we are pouring into schools,
私達は学校に注ぎ込んでいる 資源について
we should stop and ask ourselves:
立ち止まり自問すべきです
Are we really setting our kids up for success?
子ども達を成功させるお膳立てが 本当にできているのだろうか？
Now, a few years ago,
さて数年前
I was a judge on a cooking competition called "Chopped."
私は ある料理対決番組で 審査員を務めました
Four chefs compete with mystery ingredients
４人の料理人が 当日に出される課題食材を使って
to see who can cook the best dishes.
料理の味を競い合うのです
Except for this episode -- it was a very special one.
ただし この回だけは 非常に特別でした
Instead of four overzealous chefs trying to break into the limelight --
４人の料理人が脚光を浴びようと 躍起になっているのではなく—
something that I would know nothing about --
私には別世界の話ですけどね—
(Laughter)
（笑）
these chefs were school chefs;
その４人は 学校給食を作る料理人でした
you know, the women that you used to call "lunch ladies,"
かつて皆さんは「給食のおばさん」と 呼んでいたかもしれませんが
but the ones I insist we call "school chefs."
「スクールシェフ」と 呼ぶべき人達です
Now, these women -- God bless these women --
この女性達は— 全く頭が下がる思いですが—
spend their day cooking for thousands of kids,
日々何千人もの子ども達の 朝食、昼食を作り
with only about a dollar of that actually going to the food.
その内 食材費は わずか１ドル前後です
In this episode,
さて番組の この回では
the main-course mystery ingredient was quinoa.
メインコースの課題食材は キヌアでした
Now, I know it's been a long time
さて殆どの皆さんが
since most of you have had a school lunch,
給食を久しく 食べていないと思います
and we've made a lot of progress on nutrition,
給食の栄養に関しては 随分向上して来ましたが
but quinoa still is not a staple in most school cafeterias.
キヌアは 殆どの学食で まだ定番ではありません
(Laughter)
（笑）
So this was a challenge.
だからこれは難しかったのです
But the dish that I will never forget was cooked by a woman
しかし私が忘れられないのは シェリル・バーバラという
named Cheryl Barbara.
女性が作った料理です
Cheryl was the nutrition director
シェリルはコネチカット州の高校で
at High School in the Community in Connecticut.
栄養指導をしていました
She cooked this delicious pasta.
彼女が作ったのは それは美味しいパスタでした
It was amazing.
見事な出来でした
It was a pappardelle with Italian sausage,
イタリアンソーセージ、ケール パルメザンチーズ入りの
kale, Parmesan cheese.
パッパルデッレでした
It was delicious, like, restaurant-quality good, except --
れっきとしたレストランの食事 さながらの味でしたが
she basically just threw the quinoa, pretty much uncooked,
ただし 肝心のキヌアは 殆んど火を通さずに
into the dish.
料理に加えていました
It was a strange choice,
おかしなことをしたものです
and it was super crunchy.
それはもう凄い歯ごたえでした
(Laughter)
（笑）
So I took on the TV accusatory judge thing that you're supposed to do,
そこで私はテレビの審査員がよくやる 口ぶりで 何故そうしたのかを
and I asked her why she did that.
訊いてみました
Cheryl responded, "Well, first, I don't know what quinoa is."
シェリルは答えました 「最初キヌアが何か分らなかったのです」
(Laughter)
（笑）
"But I do know that it's a Monday,
「でも今日は月曜で
and that in my school, at High School in the Community,
私の勤務する学校では
I always cook pasta."
いつもパスタを作っているんです」
See, Cheryl explained that for many of her kids,
シェリルの説明によると 子ども達の多くは
there were no meals on the weekends.
週末食事をしないのだそうです
No meals on Saturday.
土曜日も食事なし
No meals on Sunday, either.
日曜日も食事なし
So she cooked pasta because she wanted to make sure
だから子ども達が喜んで 食べてくれるだろうと
she cooked something she knew her children would eat.
確信の持てるパスタを作ったのでした
Something that would stick to their ribs, she said.
彼女が作りたかったのは 子ども達に満腹感を与える物
Something that would fill them up.
子ども達の腹を満たす物でした
Cheryl talked about how, by the time Monday came,
月曜日が来るまでに
her kids' hunger pangs were so intense
子ども達の空腹の苦しみは 頂点に達し
that they couldn't even begin to think about learning.
勉強について考えることすら できなかったのです
Food was the only thing on their mind.
頭に浮かぶのはただ１つ 食べ物のこと
The only thing.
それだけなのです
And unfortunately, the stats -- they tell the same story.
残念なことに 統計からも 同じ事が分かります
So, let's put this into the context of a child.
これを子どもの状況に あてはめてみましょう
And we're going to focus on
１日の内で最も大切な食事―
the most important meal of the day, breakfast.
朝食に焦点を当ててみます
Meet Allison.
例えばアリソン
She's 12 years old,
年齢は12歳で
she's smart as a whip
とても優秀です
and she wants to be a physicist when she grows up.
大きくなったら物理学者に なりたいと思っています
If Allison goes to a school that serves a nutritious breakfast
生徒全員が 栄養価の高い給食を食べられる学校へ
to all of their kids,
この子が行ったとしたら
here's what's going to follow.
こんな事が起きます
Her chances of getting a nutritious meal,
栄養の豊富な食事 果物とミルク付きで
one with fruit and milk, one lower in sugar and salt,
糖分や塩分控えめの食事を 口にする機会が
dramatically increase.
劇的に増えるのです
Allison will have a lower rate of obesity than the average kid.
この子は平均的な子どもより 肥満になる確率が低くなり
She'll have to visit the nurse less.
病院に行く事も少なくなります
She'll have lower levels of anxiety and depression.
不安や抑うつの傾向も下がり
She'll have better behavior.
素行も良くなるでしょう
She'll have better attendance, and she'll show up on time more often.
学校への出席率も向上し 遅刻も減るでしょう
Why?
何故って？
Well, because there's a good meal waiting for her at school.
学校に行けば素敵な食事が 待っているからです
Overall, Allison is in much better health
概してアリソンは 他の平均的な子ども達より
than the average school kid.
ずっと健康的です
So what about that kid
それに対し 学校に行っても
who doesn't have a nutritious breakfast waiting for him?
栄養豊富な朝食が待っていない 子どもの場合はどうでしょう
Well, meet Tommy.
仮にトミーとします
He's also 12. He's a wonderful kid.
同じく12歳で 本当にいい子です
He wants to be a doctor.
将来の夢は医師です
By the time Tommy is in kindergarten,
幼稚園の頃にはもう
he's already underperforming in math.
数字が苦手になっています
By the time he's in third grade,
３年生になる頃にはもう
he's got lower math and reading scores.
算数と国語で 低い点数を取っています
By the time he's 11,
11歳になる頃には
it's more likely that Tommy will have to have repeated a grade.
一度は留年している 可能性が高いでしょう
Research shows that kids who do not have consistent nourishment,
研究によると 栄養不足— 特に朝食での栄養が
particularly at breakfast,
足りていない子どもは
have poor cognitive function overall.
一般的に認知機能が 低いのだそうです
So how widespread is this problem?
この問題は どれだけ 蔓延しているのでしょう？
Well, unfortunately, it's pervasive.
残念ながら かなり深刻です
Let me give you two stats
今から紹介する２つの統計は
that seem like they're on opposite ends of the issue,
それぞれ この問題において 対極にあるように見えて
but are actually two sides of the same coin.
実は表裏一体なのです
On the one hand,
まず 一方では
one in six Americans are food insecure,
アメリカの６人に１人が 満足に食べられておらず
including 16 million children -- almost 20 percent --
その中には千６百万人の子ども— 子ども全体の約20%も
are food insecure.
含まれています
In this city alone, in New York City,
ここ ニューヨーク市だけで
474,000 kids under the age of 18 face hunger every year.
18歳以下の47万4千人の子ども達が 毎年 食糧不足の状態にあります
It's crazy.
ひどい状況です
On the other hand,
その一方で
diet and nutrition is the number one cause of preventable death and disease
この国で予防可能な死亡や病気の 最大の原因になっているのは
in this country, by far.
食生活と栄養の問題です
And fully a third of the kids that we've been talking about tonight
今話題にしてきたような 子ども達の３分の１以上が
are on track to have diabetes in their lifetime.
糖尿病の予備軍なのです
Now, what's hard to put together but is true
空腹と糖尿病を 繋げて考えるのは難しいのですが
is that, many times, these are the same children.
実際 多くの場合 両方 同じ子に起きる問題なのです
So they fill up on the unhealthy and cheap calories
つまり 身の回りにありふれている 親が安く買えるような
that surround them in their communities and that their families can afford.
不健康で高カロリーの食べ物で お腹を満たしています
But then by the end of the month,
しかし その月末までに
food stamps run out or hours get cut at work,
親がフードスタンプを使い果たしたり 仕事を減らされたりすると
and they don't have the money to cover the basic cost of food.
必要最低限の食料を買うお金も なくなってしまうのです
But we should be able to solve this problem, right?
しかし私達には この問題を 解決できるはずですよね？
We know what the answers are.
答えが分かっているのですから
As part of my work at the White House, we instituted a program
ホワイトハウスでの仕事の一環で あるプログラムを策定しました
that for all schools that had 40 percent more low-income kids,
低所得層の家庭の子どもを 40％以上抱える全ての学校では
we could serve breakfast and lunch to every kid in that school.
その学校の子ども達全員に 朝食と昼食を出すというものです
For free.
しかも無料で
This program has been incredibly successful,
このプログラムは それはもう大成功
because it helped us overcome a very difficult barrier
なぜなら これが子ども達に 栄養のある朝食を摂らせる上での
when it came to getting kids a nutritious breakfast.
非常に困難な障害に 打ち勝つ助けとなったからです
And that was the barrier of stigma.
それは「不名誉」という障害です
See, schools serve breakfast before school,
学校が授業の前に出す朝食を
and it was only available for the poor kids.
今まで利用できるのは 貧しい子ども達だけだったので
So everybody knew who was poor and who needed government help.
誰が貧しくて政府の援助を 必要としていたか丸分かりでした
Now, all kids, no matter how much or how little their parents make,
どんな子どもだって どんなに親が稼ごうが稼ぐまいが
have a lot of pride.
プライドは高いのです
So what happened?
何が起きたかって？
Well, the schools that have implemented this program
このプログラムを 実施した学校では
saw an increase in math and reading scores by 17.5 percent.
算数と国語で17.5% 点数が伸びたのです
17.5 percent.
17.5%です
And research shows that when kids have a consistent, nutritious breakfast,
研究によると 子ども達が 継続的に栄養のある朝食を摂ると
their chances of graduating increase by 20 percent.
卒業できる率が 20%上昇するのです
20 percent.
20%もですよ
When we give our kids the nourishment they need,
子ども達に 必要な栄養を与えれば
we give them the chance to thrive,
彼らがすくすく育ち 学校でそしてその先も
both in the classroom and beyond.
活躍するチャンスを 与えることになります
Now, you don't have to trust me on this,
この件に関して 私の話を 鵜呑みにする必要はありませんが
but you should talk to Donna Martin.
ドナ・マーティンと 話してみれば分かります
I love Donna Martin.
私の大好きな人です
Donna Martin is the school nutrition director at Burke County
ドナはジョージア州 ウェインズボロ市にあるバーク郡の
in Waynesboro, Georgia.
学校給食指導者です
Burke County is one of the poorest districts
さてバーク郡はアメリカの
and about 100 percent of Donna's students live at or below the poverty line.
ドナの生徒達のほぼ全員が 貧困線以下の暮らしをしています
A few years ago,
数年前
Donna decided to get out ahead of the new standards that were coming,
ドナは新たな 栄養基準の更新に先駆け
and overhaul her nutrition standards.
担当地域の栄養基準を 精査し 改定しました
She improved and added fruit and vegetables and whole grains.
彼女は果物や野菜、全粒穀物を 新たに加えてメニューを改善しました
She served breakfast in the classroom to all of her kids.
郡の生徒達全員に 教室で朝食を出し さらに
And she implemented a dinner program.
夕食の提供も開始したのです
Why?
何故かって？
Well, many of her kids didn't have dinner when they went home.
子ども達の多くは家に帰っても 夕食を食べられないからです
So how did they respond?
皆の反応は どうだったのでしょう？
Well, the kids loved the food.
子ども達は大満足でした
They loved the better nutrition,
栄養満点だし
and they loved not being hungry.
お腹も満たされるからです
But Donna's biggest supporter came from an unexpected place.
しかしドナの最大の支援者は 予期せぬ所からやって来ました
His name from Eric Parker,
エリック・パーカーという人物で
and he was the head football coach for the Burke County Bears.
バークカウンティ・ベアーズという アメフトチームの主任コーチでした
Now, Coach Parker had coached mediocre teams for years.
パーカーは冴えないチームの コーチを何年もしていました
The Bears often ended in the middle of the pack --
ベアーズはだいたい 真ん中程度の成績で終わり
a big disappointment in one of the most passionate football states
国内でも一、二を争うほど アメフトに熱狂的な州の中では
in the Union.
残念な結果を出していました
But the year Donna changed the menus,
しかしドナが 食事のメニューを変えたその年に
the Bears not only won their division,
ベアーズは リーグ優勝しただけでなく
they went on to win the state championship,
州の選手権でも優勝したのです
beating the Peach County Trojans
ピーチカウンティ・トロージャンを
28-14.
28対14で破ってです
(Laughter)
（笑）
And Coach Parker,
そしてパーカーコーチは
he credited that championship to Donna Martin.
この優勝をドナ・マーティンの 功績だとしたのです
When we give our kids the basic nourishment,
子ども達に 基本的な栄養を与えれば
they're going to thrive.
すくすくと育ち 将来 活躍できるのです
And it's not just up to the Cheryl Barbaras
そしてそれは世界中にいる シェリル・バーバラや
and the Donna Martins of the world.
ドナ・マーティンのような 人達だけでなく
It's on all of us.
私達皆の責任なのです
And feeding our kids the basic nutrition is just the starting point.
子ども達に基本的な栄養を与える事は スタート地点に過ぎません
What I've laid out is really a model
今 説明したのは 私達が数多く直面する—
for so many of the most pressing issues that we face.
最も差し迫った課題の １つの解決法に過ぎません
If we focus on the simple goal of properly nourishing ourselves,
適切な栄養を摂るという シンプルな目標に焦点を合わせると
we could see a world that is more stable and secure;
より安全で 揺るぎない世界が 見えてきます
we could dramatically improve our economic productivity;
経済においては生産性が向上し
we could transform our health care
医療も改善し
and we could go a long way
さらには地球資源を確実に
in ensuring that the Earth can provide for generations to come.
子や孫の代まで 存続させられるのです
Food is that place where our collective efforts
食こそ 私達 皆の力を合わせる事の効果が
can have the greatest impact.
最も表れる分野です
So we have to ask ourselves: What is the right question?
だから私達は自問せねばなりません 正しい質問とは何かと
What would happen
より栄養豊富で
if we fed ourselves more nutritious, more sustainably grown food?
自然環境に優しく育てられた食物を 摂ったらどうなるだろうか？
What would be the impact?
どんな効果があるだろうか？
Cheryl Barbara,
シェリル・バーバラ
Donna Martin,
ドナ・マーティン
Coach Parker and the Burke County Bears --
パーカーコーチや バークカウンティ・ベアーズの
I think they know the answer.
皆がその答えを知っています
Thank you guys so very much.
ありがとうございました
(Applause)
（拍手）